[Music]
hello and welcome to episode 12 of the
inventory tutorial series and episode
one of the shop system
in our shop system and there's not much
really visibly to show kind of in-game
you can see we've got these three uh
capsules here these are gonna be our
shop npcs so we can see here we've got
shop and pc
and it's got a shop system and it's got
three items and it's holding different
amounts of those items
we've got our shop npc here this is the
weapon shop it's got 10 swords available
got the shopkeeper here this is the
potion shop and it's got
50 of the health and poison potions
which you can see in the world so
there's a poison and health potions
and this is all defined by these
scriptable objects here so we go to our
potion shop we can see that i've said
that we've got 50 poison potions
and 50 health potions as well as the
shop having a kind of available gold
that can be
used to buy items from the player
and each one of these has different
values and that's driving these shops
with the shop npcs as we're going to get
to by the end of this video uh so let's
just jump straight into it
okay so let's just get started um so to
start with i'm going to right click
create a folder we can call this um shop
system and let's enter this folder and
i'm gonna right click create um just a
few scripts so i'm gonna create a um
shop
item list this is gonna be a scriptable
object um script this will allow us to
define which items a shop is selling and
how many of them they've got as well as
how much gold that that um shop has
access to for buying items from the
player and a way of influencing the
price of items to either make them a
little bit more expensive or
buy them for less money than the worth
but you'll see that as we kind of go
along that that's how we can do that so
let's just open this script up um okay
so we've got our script here so instead
of model behavior let's derive this from
scriptable object and then let's um make
a create asset menu and we can do menu
name is equal to um we'll do shop system
forward slash uh shop item list so as i
said this is gonna be everything that
the um shop has in stock okay so the
first thing we're gonna do is we're
gonna have a serialized field uh private
list of um shop inventory item which is
a new class that we're gonna make and
i'm just going to call this uh
underscore items we'll have a serialized
field
private int max allowed gold sorry again
of that like that i'm going to do a
serialized field private float and this
is our cell markup and we'll have a
serialized field private float
by so let's create this um shop
inventory item now and what this is
going to be is it's just going to be a
struct so we can come out with our class
here and we'll just do a public struct
um shop inventory item and this is just
gonna have a public uh inventory item
data called item data as well as a
public ant um amount i need to make sure
my item convention names are all we've
got our shop inventory item here and we
need to mark this as serializable so
we're gonna do system dot serializable
okay so now we need to make a shop um
keeper which is going to be the mpc in
the world that holds our um shop
inventory and it's going to be kind of
like the inventory holder script we've
got so let's go back over to our project
and we can right-click create and we'll
create another c-sharp script and we'll
call this um shopkeeper and again we can
go and open this up so
shop system shopkeeper so our shopkeeper
is going to be kind of like um chest or
other items in the world that we want to
save because we're going to be
influencing their inventory we want to
be able to save them out because there's
going to be multiple of them we need to
use our unique id component so we'll
just say require component type of
unique id and then it's going to be a
mono behavior and it's going to inherit
from i interactable as well because
we're going to need to interact with the
npc so we can implement the missing
members from our
interactable interface i will implement
these um soon we're not going to use
them straight away and let's just get
rid of these for now as well and what
i'm going to do is i'm going to create a
serialized field and this will be a
private um shop item list and we'll call
this a shop items held so this is going
to control
um again which kind of items the shop is
selling and this will be here and then
we need to create a shop system which
lives on our shopkeeper
to kind of hold and manage the shop
interface and now this is kind of like
we've got the inventory holder which has
an inventory system now we've got a
shopkeeper which is going to have a shop
system so again go back to unity right
click create c-sharp crypt crypt c sharp
script and we'll have a shop system
script then on our shopkeeper we can
have a private field we have a private
um shop system called this shop system
now let's jump into our shop system
script so it's going to have some
similar functionality to our inventory
system script but it's not going to
derive from that we're going to kind of
copy some of the code over where we need
to but it does
so much different that it's not sort of
i don't really see the point of making
kind of like a parent class to inherit
from so the first thing i want to do in
our shop system is let's make a
constructor so i'm going to say public
shop system and this can take in an int
for the size of the system and in the
amount of gold that the system will have
a float for our um buy mark up and a
float for the cell art book and then up
here we need to just make a private int
we can say available gold and we can set
available gold to gold from our um
constructor we'll need a private float
and buy markup as well as a private
float cell mark oh and again let's do
buy markup is equal to i marco and cell
markup is equal to cell markup and then
i'm going to make a public um and then
i'm going to make a private void uh set
shop size uh method and this will take
in
the int size and what this will do is
we'll set all this up and then we'll set
the shop size and we'll pass in our size
and the kind of main thing that this is
going to do is it's going to um create a
list of shop slots which is another
class we'll have to make so let's do a
private
um
list of shops slot and we'll call this
our shop inventory and before we make
this method let's make this class so
we're going to go back to
um our project and now we're going to
right click create c-sharp script and
we'll call this one shot slot now we're
going to have to um do a bit of
refactoring
to get this to work so let's get rid of
start an update and i'm going to open up
our um inventory slot script here which
is uh one that we made way back when i'm
just going to open these up side by side
so i'm actually going to put a lot of
this functionality into something called
an item slot and then the inventory slot
will inherit from item slot so again
we'll go back over here we'll right
click create and i'm actually going to
put this um i'm actually going to put
this in our item scripts folder so i'm
going to right click create c sharp
script and we'll call this one item slot
oh we've got item slot here and actually
need to let's have these open side by
side if you can split them uh i would do
it makes this a lot easier so um or item
slot that's going to implement i
serialization callback receiver so we
can um implement those missing members
and then inventory slot is going to
inherit from item slot and item slot is
going to be an abstract class we've got
public abstract class item slot and
that's where our inventory slot is going
to inherit from and then we can actually
copy all of this to our item slot um
class so let's get rid of let's get this
we're going to control x to copy it and
we're going to paste it cut it and we're
going to paste it over here you see that
we need to import um missing members
there and instead of being private these
now need to be protected so the um this
class can access them but no other class
can so protected i'm going to start
moving some of these methods over so
public void clear slot i'm going to take
clear slot and i'm going to put that
onto the item slot um class assign item
i'm going to take that and we'll cut it
and we'll pop it over on the item slot
uh function the item slot class you can
see the add to stack is now um red so we
need to take add to stack and remove
from stack let's cut them and then we'll
pop them onto our
item slot class and now in inventory
slot we don't need this um on after the
serialize so we can take this and we'll
cut this into
this method here and we'll get rid of
this exception and we can get rid of
these so now in our inventory slot um
we've still got access to all of these
methods because again we're inheriting
from item slot now and we've just left
um so on inventory slot we've now got um
our enough room left in stack methods
our split stack method a constructor to
make an inventory slot that just sets it
up as a clear slot and this other
constructor here um the reason that
we've got we haven't copied these over
to item slot is that we don't need to
check on a shop slot if there's enough
room in the stack so i've basically what
i've done here is i've taken uh the
stacking ability uh functionality out of
um the shop slot because shops don't
need to stack it's going to just show a
list of an item and how many it's got it
doesn't care about stacks because i'd
look really weird in the ui to have
multiple entries for the same item just
showing different stacks so an inventory
slot can stack a shop slot can't so but
a shop slot um needs to be able to kind
of add items to it remove items from it
and you know access its save data and be
able to assign an item to it so that is
shared functionality so that's why we've
put this into our abstract item slot
class so now if we go back to shop slot
this can inherit from an item slot and
then all this is going to do is when we
make a new shop slot is it's just going
to create a clear slot now in our shop
system we've got our list of shop slots
i can close our inventory slot um
functionality and first let's just make
sure that we've not broken anything
crazy um with our normal inventory
system so we can go over to play and we
can pick up our items and they're all
still stacking uh nicely we can go over
to our inventory and we can put the
items in the inventory so that's working
uh fine so we've not broken anything
there which is always a plus so now on
our shop system uh back in our private
void set shop size um function we're
just gonna set our shop inventory equal
to a new list shop slots with the size
that we define and then we're to say um
for int or int i equals zero and whilst
i is less than the size we're going to
get our shop inventory and we're gonna
add a new um shop slot to our
shop size so we've created a new shop
inventory and we've filled it with our
slots so now if we go back over to our
shop keeper in the um awake function we
can say shop system is equal to a new
shop system and this is going to take in
um so the size is going to be the amount
of items that it held so shop system
shop items held dot um items dot count
and we need to go to our shop item list
and be able to get access to our items
we're going to need to make um
public getters for all of these so we
say public list of shop inventory item
called items this just returns items
public int
max allowed gold this can return max
allowed gold okay so i've done that
there we've will get us in for our um
fields here so we go back to shopkeeper
so we're gonna pass in the items count
the um items held
max allowed gold the um terms held by
markup and the shop items held cell
markup i'm just going to drop this down
to a new line so it will fit some on
screen so we've got our shop system here
uh shop system we need to get rid of
mono behavior as well then we're going
to add the items from our list to our
shop system so we can say for each
variable item in the shop
uh items held our items let's add it to
our uh shop system so shopsystem.add to
shop which is a method that we're going
to need to make i'm going to pass in the
item
item data as well as the item dot item
dot amount pop over to our shop system
and let's make that method so public
void add to which is going to take in an
inventory item data called data and an
int amount so this is going to be quite
similar to our inventory system so let's
get our inventory system script open i'm
going to put this uh next to it in this
window here so we've got our add to
inventory here and we're gonna need to
do some similar stuff but not the exact
same so that's why i'm not uh deriving
this from like an item system uh we can
just copy it over for the most part so
the main thing is it's a contained item
let's just copy this over and then we'll
have to change some of the code so copy
that paste it over so we've got
contained uh item zoom out just a tiny
bit so instead of passing out a list of
inventory slots this is just gonna pass
out a shop slot and it's going to pass
out and here we're going to say shop
slot is equal to chop inventory is equal
to shop inventory dot find which is a um
function so we'll do shopping inventory
dot find and say
i for item so if the item data equal to
the item to add which we've passed in
here and we're just going to find the
first one and then we can return
whether um return shop slot is not equal
to null so if we found the item already
in the shop then we're gonna get the
shop slot that that item is uh in and
then shop slot won't be null so it will
return that it's not equal to null it'll
be true so it'll say yep we contain the
item and if it returns false and if it
is null because it hasn't found the item
it'll return false so in our add to shop
we can say that if contains item we can
pass in the data and get back out the um
shop slot let's put shop slot and we're
just going to add the amount to the
stack and again we don't care about like
enough room left in the stack on a shop
slot it's just can it can hold an
infinite amount of items so we'll say
add to stack the shop doesn't already
contain the item we need to get um a
free slot and that's just going to make
a new slot so we can say
um our three slot is equal to get free
slot and then this can be a private
function which returns a shop slot so
private shop slot get three slot and all
this is gonna do is um gonna make a free
slot and it's just gonna find the um
shop inventory up first or default and
it's gonna find the first slot where the
slots data is equal to null and if for
some reason our free slot is equal to
null so if it hasn't found a empty slot
then our shop can have as many slots as
it needs so all we're going to do then
just as a bit of a fail safe we can do
three slot is equal to a new shop slot
we'll add that slot to the inventory so
we're going to add the pre-slot and then
we're just going to return our free slot
so this will never be null we're always
going to get a slot ideally it'll be the
one from our inventory but just as a
fail safe as i said we can create a new
one and add this to the inventory we can
always get the free slot up here and
then we can assign three slot dot assign
item and we'll pass in our data and
amount and this is complaining because
we need to put from our inventory slot
okay so on our item slot we need to make
a another function that assigns an item
by taking in some data and amount so
public void assign item and this will
take in inventory item data called data
and it'll take in an int for the amount
and if the slot already contains data so
if item data is equal to data let's just
add to the stack the amount else item
data is uh equal to data item id is
equal to the data dot id stack size is
equal to zero just to default it out and
then we can just add to stack the amount
so back over on our shop system so we're
going to add it to the shop if it
contains the item we'll just add to the
stack and if it doesn't then we're gonna
make a new slot and assign the data to
it so back in our shop system uh back in
our shopkeeper we can now see
this method here and that's all working
so when the shopkeeper um when the game
starts we're gonna make a new shop
system and then we're gonna add uh an
item to the stock of that shop so we're
gonna loop through all of the items that
the shop holds we're gonna add it to our
shop system and that's it for the
shopkeeper for now okay so let's make an
mpc to try and interact with so i'm
going to come over to our scene here and
i'm going to right click create an empty
and i'm just going to call this our shop
mpc and i'm going to right click create
3d object
capsule so this is our shop npc so let's
drop the shopkeeper script onto it you
can see that it needs a um item held
list i'm going to get this and let's
bring that over here you can see we've
got a bit of an issue here where it
already adds a script when it adds the
unique id script to an object um it's
not working straight away so let's just
um we can do uh context menu and
generate id and we can just uh generate
an id for that to get rid of the error
that we were having so now in our shop
system let's create a folder called um
shop item list so for scriptable objects
and we can right click create chop
system shop item list and we'll just
call this
default shop list for now or the max
allowed gold let's say the shop keeper
can start with
a thousand gold and for the markup this
can be um this is going to be a
percentage so we could say it's going to
mark up the price by 25 by 25 so if
something is um you know worth 100 gold
so and what that's doing is if we look
into our item data folder you can see
we've got our gold value here which is
going to be
um set to something like 100 for example
and that's kind of a base value now
using these markups if uh if i put 0.25
here and say 0.5 in the buy markup what
this is going to do eventually is that
when we try to
sell a um if we try and sell that cog
which is worth 100 to the shopkeeper
he's actually only going to offer us 75
gold four instead of 100 because he's
going to take 25 off and then he will
sell cogs to us for 150 gold so that's
kind of the markup and so now you've got
to think of these as kind of like a base
value this is kind of you know so in an
ideal world if a shop really likes you
for example they're not going to mark it
up this how much it's going to cost but
we've now got that flexibility to kind
of you know rip off the player or even
reward the player we can offer them more
um more than the actual value if for
example that npc really wants certain
items um or really likes you they can
you can specify that here
and in our items um list we can now drop
in um some stock so we can open up this
and we can say cog but the shop is going
to stock 99 cogs and
let's say it will stock 10 potions and
let's say it can stock um one sword so
that's its stock list we can go back
over to our shop npc and let's add our
default shop item list to that and then
let's just um we're not going to get the
ui set up in this video um but let's
just put a debug dot login so back on
our shop system so over on our
shopkeeper script and we'll say for each
item in shop items held let's just debug
dot log um item and we'll make a new
string and we'll say um item dot
item data dot display name and then
we'll put a colon and we'll put in the
item dot amount so this is just gonna
debug.log every item um that's getting
added to the shop and the amount of that
item as well so if we hit play you can
see that when we've set up our
shopkeeper system we've got our cogs 99
health potion 10 and the shop contains
one sword now and if we go over to our
shop system and we can actually add a
system.serializable
uh to our shop system so we've got our
shop system so after we've added
system.serializable
uh we can serialize these fields and we
should be able to see them in the
inspector we'll do serialized fields
serialized field and then if we go over
to our shopkeeper let's serialize this
field as well and then if we go over to
shop slot we also need to mark this as
system.serializable as well and now this
is serializable the shopkeeper is
serializable so if we go back to unity
we should be able to see this all in the
inspector so we've got shop inventory
and we can see our inventory there so if
we hit play we can now see our shop
inventory has 99 of item id2 it's got 10
of item id 50 and
one of item id 0 and we can see that our
cog has an id of two we've got our cog
here we've got 99 of them our shop nbc
as 99 of item two so the great thing
about this is we're gonna have multiple
npcs now so if we um control d and
duplicate our pc and make another one
and it's got the same list so let's
right click create shop item list and
we'll say um weapon shop and this can be
a shop that has all of our weapons we've
only got one um item here but let's say
it carries 10 swords it can have 2 000
gold it's got a cell markup of 1.5 and a
by markup of 1.5 now we'll go back over
to our mpc we'll give it the new sort of
stock list we'll hit play you can now
see that this has got ten swords this
one has only got one sword but it's got
all of our other items and we've defined
all of these different things in our
shop systems and again to show you kind
of how easy it is we can make shop
system and we'll say potion shop this
will stock two items it'll stock the
poison potion and the health potion and
it'll have 50 of each they'll have 500
gold but they're gonna rip you off with
the um with the markup and then we can
make a another bean this will be our
potion shop so we'll make a potion shop
hit play so we've got three individual
um shops here so we've got our npc here
which has got the default shop list
we've got this npc which is a is a
weapon shop we've got this npc which is
a potion shop so that's going to be it
for this video um and it was a lot of
like jumping between different scripts
and refactoring stuff but that's kind of
the way these things go
um but hopefully that all made sense and
if you followed if you've got to this
point in the inventory tutorial system
uh hopefully it will all make sense
because these are scripts that we've
kind of dove in and out of numerous
times and it's a lot of the kind of same
concepts of the sort of inventory system
so if i skipped over anything um quickly
maybe go back and watch the previous
videos to kind of get up to speed with
for example how the contained item
function works or you know whatever um
in the next video we'll start to set up
the ui for the shopkeeper which will
display their inventory in a list and
we'll see how far we get with that um
whether we have to make another video
about actually purchasing and selling
items to the shop if you want access to
the project files from this video you
can head over to
patreon.com where they are available i'd
just like to take a minute to thank all
of my patrons on screen now we can see
the 10 000 xp tier which is a sector
sweep and i want to thank all of the 4
000 xp tier members as well if you need
any help with this video make sure you
head over to the discord server which is
linked in the description below or just
leave a comment on the video and i'll do
my best to help you there but in the
meantime thanks for watching i'll catch
you in the next one bye
you